In this video, I look at
common cookware materials—
aluminum, stainless steel,
and cast iron.
Watch the video to find out
which might be best to use.
"Are Aluminum, Stainless Steel,
Cast Iron, and Teflon Safe?"
Over the last decades, the toxicity
of aluminum for humans
has been heavily discussed and
is still not completely clarified.
Those occupationally exposed
to aluminum in like smelter plants
suffer from oxidative stress, free
radicals, that can damage their DNA.
But what about just using
aluminum cookware?
Articles like this, suggesting an
unrecognized public health risk,
was limited to the developing world
where cookware is made in informal shops
by casting liquid aluminum melted
from a collection of scrap metal,
including the likes of lead batteries,
which is how you can get
so much lead leaching into peoples' food.
But then this study was published
suggesting the aluminum
itself may be harmful.
Most of our aluminum exposure comes
from processed junk that contains
aluminum-containing food additives,
including those within some processed
cheeses, baking powders, cake mixes,
frozen dough, and pancake mixes.
But approximately 20% of the daily
intake of aluminum may come
from aluminum cooking utensils,
such as pans, pots, kettles, and trays.
To see if this may be causing a problem,
they took blood from consumers
that used aluminum cookware
versus those that did not,
and found that not only were the
aluminum users walking around
with twice the level of
aluminum in their blood,
but they had more free radical damage
of their body fats and proteins.
And the total antioxidant capacity of
their bloodstream was compromised,
so, no surprise, suffered
significantly more DNA damage.
And indeed, those with the highest
levels of aluminum in their blood
tended to suffer significantly
more damage to their DNA.
No surprise, since aluminum is
considered to be a pro-oxidant agent.
These folks weren't just casually
using aluminum pots, though,
but specifically using them daily
to cook and store acidic foods,
like yogurt and tomato sauce, which
can leach out more aluminum.
But even just a week using like camping
dishes, which tend to be aluminum
since it's so light, if you were
incorporating something acidic,
like marinating a fresh catch in
lemon juice, could greatly exceed
the tolerable weekly intake
guidelines, especially for children.
Once in a while is not going to make much
of a difference, but this suggests that
you may not want to be cooking
in aluminum day-in and day-out.
What about aluminum drinking bottles?
They're nice and light but children
drinking two cups of tea or juice
a day from them could exceed the
tolerable aluminum exposure limit.
So out of an abundance of
caution, safety authorities,
like the German Federal Institute
for Risk Assessment,
recommend that consumers avoid
the use of aluminum pots or dishes
for acidic or salted foodstuffs such
as apple sauce, rhubarb, tomato puree,
or salt herring to avoid any
unnecessary ingestion of aluminum.
What about aluminum foil?
It's a common culinary practice to
wrap food in aluminum foil and bake it.
The concern is that this
could potentially present
a hazardous source of
aluminum in the human diet.
When put to the test, yes, there
was leakage from the foil to the food,
but the amount was so small that it would
be more of an issue for small children
or those suffering from
diminished kidney function.
What about just wrapping of food
in foil to store in the fridge?
Only marginal increases in aluminum
are seen, unless the food is in contact
with both the foil and, at the same
time, certain other types of metal,
for example stainless steel,
which is largely iron.
And so that sets up a battery and so
can lead to tremendous food aluminum
concentrations. For example, here
are the aluminum levels in a ham
before and after a day covered
in foil. But take that same ham
and that same day of foil on top
of a steel tray or serving plate,
and the aluminum levels
in the ham shoots up.
And finally, you know how there's
sometimes a glossy side
of aluminum foil and then a dull side?
Which would be worse?
Fish fillets were baked and grilled
both ways, wrapped in the glossy side
versus wrapped in the dull side, and
no significant difference was found.
In my last video I expressed concerns
about the use of aluminum cookware.
So, what’s the best type
of pots and pans to use?
Stainless steel is an excellent option,
the metal chosen in applications where
safety and hygiene are considered
to be of the utmost importance,
such as kitchenware.
But what about studies showing
stainless steel can leach
nickel and chromium into
foods during cooking?
(That’s what keeps the iron in the
stainless steel unstained by rust.)
The leaching is really only
when they’re brand new.
Metal leaching decreases with
sequential cooking cycles
and stabilizes after the
sixth time you cook with it.
Under more common
day-to-day conditions,
the use of stainless-steel pots
is considered to be safe
even for most people who are
acutely sensitive to those metals.
A little leaching metal can be a good
thing in the case of straight iron,
like a cast iron skillet, which
can have the beneficial effect
of helping to improve iron status,
helping to potentially reduce
the incidence of iron deficiency anemia
among reproductive age
women and children.
The only caveat is that you don’t
want to be frying in cast iron.
Frying isn’t healthy regardless,
but at hot temperatures
vegetable oil can react with
the iron to create trans fats.
What about using nonstick pans?
Teflon, also known as
polytetrafluoroethylene,
is used as an inner coating
material in nonstick cookware.
Teflon’s dark history was the subject
of a recent movie called Dark Waters,
starring Mark Ruffalo
and Anne Hathaway.
Employees in DuPont’s Teflon division
started giving birth to
deformed babies before DuPont
“removed all female staff” from the unit.
Of course, they buried it all, hiding
it from regulators and the public.
Despite this significant
history of industry knowledge
about how toxic some of the
chemicals used to make Teflon were,
they were able to keep it all hidden.
But eventually they were forced to
settle for over half a billion dollars
after one of the chemicals was linked
to kidney and testicular cancers,
pregnancy-induced hypertension,
ulcerative colitis, and high cholesterol.
“At normal cooking temperatures,
[Teflon]-coated cookware releases
various gases and chemicals that
present mild to severe toxicity.”
Here’s some of the different gases that
are released at different temperatures
and the toxic effects that
have been documented.
You’ve heard of canaries in a coal mine?
They're more like canaries in the kitchen,
as cooking with Teflon cookware is well
known to kill pet birds in the house;
or Teflon coated heat lamp bulbs
wiping out half a chicken flock.
“Apart from the gases released
during heating the cooking pans,
the coating itself starts
damaging after a certain period.
It's normally advised to use slow heating
when cooking in Teflon-coated pans,”
but you can imagine how
consumers might ignore that.
And some of the Teflon can start
chipping off if you’re not careful
and make its way into the food, though
the effects of ingestion are unknown.
This is the only study I could
find looking at the potential
human health effects of cooking
with nonstick pots and pans,
and the use of non-stick
cookware was associated with
about a 50 percent increased
risk of colorectal cancer.
But that may be because
of what they were cooking.
Non-stick cookware is used in
hazardous high-heat cooking methods,
like broiling, frying, grilling,
or barbecuing, mainly for meat,
poultry or fish, in which
carcinogenic heterocyclic amines
are formed from the animal protein.
And then the animal fat can
produce another class of carcinogens
called polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons.
Though it’s possible it
was the Teflon itself,
which contains suspected carcinogens
like that C8 compound from the movie,
also known as PFOA,
perfluorooctanoic acid.
“Due to toxicity concerns,
this chemical has been replaced
with other chemicals such as
GenX, but these new alternatives
are also suspected to
have similar toxicity.”
But we’ve already so contaminated the
Earth with it that we now can get it
prepackaged in food before it’s
even cooked, particularly in fish,
dairy products, and meat,
which is now the main source
of human exposure to
these toxic pollutants.
Of those, seafood is the worst.
In a study of diets from around the world,
fish and seafood were major contributors
of the perfluoroalkyl substances,
as expected, given that everything
eventually flows into the sea.
Though the aquatic food chain
is the primary transfer mechanism
for these toxins into the human
diet, “food stored or prepared
in greaseproof packaging
materials,” like microwave popcorn,
may also be a source.
And in 2019, Oral-B Glide
dental floss was tested.
6 out of 18 dental floss products
they tested showed evidence
of Teflon-type compounds.
Here’s the list.
So, did those who used
those kinds of floss
end up with higher levels
in their blood stream?
Yes, apparently so.
Higher levels of
perfluorohexanesulfonic acid
were found in Oral-B Glide flossers.
There’s lots of environmental
exposures in the modern world
we can’t avoid, but we
shouldn’t be making things worse
by adding it to consumer products.
But hey, at least it gives
us some power to lower
our personal exposure to
these harmful chemicals.